Guide to the Department of Theater Studies Records, circa 1968-2004 UA.25.40.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Department of Theater Studies Records
circa 1968-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Department of Theater Studies
UA.25.40.0002
6.5 Linear Feet
The Department of Theater Studies at Duke University offers courses on the critical evaluation, writing and performance of dramatic works. The department seeks to promote an artistic culture at Duke by bringing professional theatrical performances to campus. The Department of Theater Studies records is composed of administrative materials and records related to both departmental and professional performances staged at Duke.
Historical Note
In 2001, the Drama Studies program at Duke University was reorganized into the Department of Theater Studies. The Department of Theater Studies provides students with opportunity to critically study theatrical works and stage dramatic productions. In the 1980s the department strove to extend its national reputation by recruiting David Ball from Carnegie Mellon University. Ball served as director of the program from 1985-1991 and recruited many prominent faculty members to join the department. In 1992, Ball was replaced by Richard Riddell who oversaw the creation of the Theater Studies department and the continued growth of the program and the improvement of theater facilities. The Theater Studies Department sponsors a student organization, the Duke Players, who contribute to productions and promote theater studies among the student body. The Duke Players also create an original "Orientation Show" for incoming freshman and stage a lab production each semester. The department also collaborates with the Music and Dance departments and with student groups such as Hoof'N'Horn and Duke Improv.
In 1986, Duke collaborated with Broadway producer Emanuel Azenberg to create the Broadway Previews series. Under the management of the Department of Theater Studies, professional theater productions were staged at Duke's Page Auditorium before they moved to Broadway. The series was intended to promote artistic culture in the Durham area and give Duke students an opportunity for internships with theater professionals. The series featured many prominent actors including Jack Lemmon in A Long Day's Journey into Night (1986), Sam Waterston in A Week in the Woods (1988), Mikhail Baryshnikov in Metamorphosis (1989), Julie Harris in Lucifer's Child (1991) and Tom Selleck in A Thousand Clowns (2001). In the 1990's the Broadway Previews series was renamed Theater Previews and continues to bring professional productions to campus today.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
Collection Overview
The Department of Theater Studies Records, 1969-2002 contains correspondence, planning documents, slides, photographs and audiovisual materials related to the administration of the department. The collection also includes materials from a diverse array of student and faculty theater productions. The Department of Theater Studies Records also contains correspondence, planning documents, clippings, promotional materials, slides, photographs, audiovisual materials and electronic records from professional productions brought to campus through the Theater Previews series.
College theater; Riddell, Richard V.; Azenberg, Emanuel; Duke University. Duke Players; Duke University. Theatre Previews at Duke; Ball, David
- Departmental Materials, 1968-2004; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Departmental Materials series contains academic and administrative materials produced by the Drama Program and the successive Department of Theater Studies. The materials have been organized into two subseries. The Administration subseries includes departmental records and the Performances subseries is comprised of materials related to student and faculty productions.
  - Performances, 1968-2004; 1
    Conditions Governing Access
    Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
    The Performances subseries features materials from productions staged by students and faculty including playbills, slides, photographs, and visual materials in betacam and VHS format. Performances featured in this subseries include Hamlet, Servant of Two Masters, Second Shepard, Noel Coward Revue, Kaspar, Noises Off, and many others. The collection also includes slides from various Duke Players productions organized chronologically between the years 1968-1986.
    - Duke Players undated, 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Duke Players undated, 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Duke Players, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Duke Players, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Duke Players, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Duke Players, 1 of 2, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Duke Players, 2 of 2, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Duke Players, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Duke Players, 1 of 2, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Duke Players, 2 of 2, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Duke Players, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Duke Players, 1 of 2, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Duke Players, 2 of 2, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Duke Players, 1 of 2, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Duke Players, 2 of 2, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Duke Players, Pre-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Duke Players, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Duke Players, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Duke Players, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Duke Players, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Kaspar (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Madwoman, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Misc. Slides (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Misc. Photos, 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Misc. Photos, 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Summer, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Circus Cervantes, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - World Premiere Festival, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Aresnic and Lace, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - WPFA, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - MacBeth, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Stagedoor, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Medal of Honor, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Hamlet, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - OCRG, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - The Trojan Woman, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - He Who Gets Slapped, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Three Cuckholds (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Cymbeline, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Mad Dog Blues, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - World Premiere Festival, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Servant of Two Masters, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Noel Coward Revue, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Butterfly's Evil Spell, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - World Premiere Festival, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Second Shepard, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Duke Students (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 20th Century Romance, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Playbills, 1986-2004 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Film Negatives (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - KASPAR-Moby Dick, 11/10/1993; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0001)
      Duke Drama, KASPAR: Tech/Dress, Moby Dick: Performance
    - KASPAR, 11/10/1993; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0002)
      Duke Drama, Cast Warm-Up w/Rafael
    - KASPAR, 11/5/1993; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0003)
    - Woman@Point Zero, 4/1/1994; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0004)
      Play: Woman at Point Zero
    - Sound Bites, 4/9/1994; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0005)
      Drama Board
    - Devon #1, 4/11/1994; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0006)
    - Devon #2, 4/11/1994; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0007)
    - Devon #3, 4/11/1994; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0008)
    - Devon-Rehearse, betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0009)
    - Noises Off!, betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0010)
      Richard Riddell, 5:00 Meeting in Schaffer
    - Noises Off!, 2/23/1994; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0011)
    - Measure for Measure, 2/13/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0012)
      Duke Drama
    - Measure + Apartment, 2/13/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0013)
    - Model Apt, 2/13/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0014)
    - Measure for Measure, 2/21/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0015)
      Duke Drama, Backstage/Rehearsal
    - Measure for Measure, 2/21/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0016)
    - Measure for Measure, 2/24/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0017)
      Duke Drama, Performance
    - Measure for Measure, 2/24/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0018)
    - Measure for Measure, 2/24/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0019)
    - Model Apt, 2/15/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0020)
    - Epworth Balcony + Contese, 3/15/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0021)
    - Kendra Drama Video, 3/20/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0022)
    - Lighting Class, Richard Riddell, 3/21/1995; betacam-sp (Box 4, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0023)
    - Richard Riddell, Eptarions, West's Class, 3/21/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0024)
    - Wests Class, Stoners Class, 3/22/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0025)
    - Stoner's Class, Hanni Int., 3/22/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0026)
    - Hanni Int., Dave's Shop, 3/22/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0027)
    - Dave's Shop, David Wainer Int., 3/23/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0028)
    - David Wainer Int. ,B-Roll, 3/23/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0029)
    - Manny Class, betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0030)
    - McAuliffe-Class, betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0031)
    - Nan Kohan, 5/5/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0032)
      Duke Drama, London Footage
    - Sounds Dangerous, 9/27/1990; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0033)
      Tape 1
    - Sounds Dangerous, 9/23/1990; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0034)
    - Sounds Dangerous-Dress Rehearsal, 9/27/1990; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0035)
    - Sounds Dangerous-Dress Rehearsal, 9/29/1990; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0036)
      Tape 2
    - Sounds Dangerous, 11/8/1990; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0037)
      Chris-Nick-pickups
    - Sounds Dangerous, betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0038)
      Extra Scenes
    - Tom Story, 3/7/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0039)
      Duke Drama, B-Roll
    - Contesse+ Walking Shot, 3/15/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0040)
      Duke Drama, 2:00 apt on tape after Drew's walk
    - Taku,Gazebo, 3/15/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0041)
    - Bavaziota Creme, Gertrude, 4/14/1995; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0042)
    - Theater Cutaways, 11/29/1993; betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0043)
    - Theater #1, betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0044)
      Interviews: David, Jen, Public: Sammy Leonard
    - Theater #2, betacam-sp (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0045)
    - Helen, 12/2/1999; VHS (Box 5, Video-cassette UA254002-Hi8-0001)
      Duke Players, 1:40:00, Finished and Edits by Cable 13
    - Theater #3, betacam-sp (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0046)
    - Theater #4, betacam-sp (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0047)
    - Theater #5, betacam-sp (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0048)
    - Theater #6, betacam-sp (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0049)
    - Zoe Caldwell, betacam-sp (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0050)
    - Gusso/Sharp/Vasquez, betacam-sp (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0051)
    - Unlabled, 1/4-inch (Box 6, Audio-reel UA254002-RR-0001)
      Performance footage for NY
    - Unlabled, 1/4-inch (Box 6, Audio-reel UA254002-RR-0002)
    - Unlabled, 1/4-inch (Box 6, Audio-reel UA254002-RR-0003)
    - Unlabled, 1/4-inch (Box 6, Audio-reel UA254002-RR-0004)
    - Bob Hope Les Brown Tribute, VHS (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-VHS-0002)
    - Duke Drama Program, VHS (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-VHS-0006)
      North Carolina Now
    - Production Photos 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Production Photos 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Production Photos 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Production Photos 4 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Production Photos 5 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Production Photos 6 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Production Photos 7 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Production Photos 8 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Production Photos 9 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Production Photos 10 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Posters, 2011-2015 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Posters, 2016-2017 (Oversize-folder 2)
    - Posters, 2018-2019 and undated (Oversize-folder 3)
    - Playbills, 2010-2018 (Box 9)
  - Administration, 1993-2002; 2
    The Administration subseries consists of correspondence, reports, clippings and other records related to the management of the Theater Studies department. These materials highlight efforts in the 1980s by program director David Ball to grow the national reputation of Duke Drama by recruiting prominent faculty and renovating theater facilities. Also included are planning documents, reports and informational interviews regarding the evolution from Drama Program to the formal Theater Studies department in 1990s.
    - Planning Documents, 1994-2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - New Drama Center, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Duke News Service, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - DUMC- Cultural Affairs, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Audit: Interviews, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Audit: People to Interview, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Communications Plan, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Communications Plan: Notes, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Internships, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Groundbreaking, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Course Listings (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Flyers (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Theater Studies Undergraduate Guide, 2011-2012 (Box 9)
    - Diploma Ceremony Program, 2016 (Box 9)
    - Fliers, undated (Box 9)
- Theater Previews, 1988-2001; 2
  The Theater Previews series contains materials from professional performances staged at Duke. Materials include playbills, clippings, promotional materials, slides, and photographs for individual productions. The series also contains video formats such as VHS and beta-cam, audio materials such as audio-cassettes and reel tape as well as electronic records. The series also features administrative records including correspondence with producers, financial and box office information, promotional strategies, and an internal program evaluation.
  Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
  - One-Thousand Clowns:Slides, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Lucifer's Child, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - R.Crumb Comix, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Broadway Preview Series, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Expenses (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Misc. Clippings (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Resources (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Producer's Letter/Mailing, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ted Snowden Productions (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Program Analysis (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1492 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Calamity Jane, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Camp Logan, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Carbondale Dreams, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Dennis the Menance, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lucifer's Child, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Lucifer's Child: Contract and Financial Information, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lucifer's Child: Clippings, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - A Thousand Clowns, 1 of 2, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - A Thousand Clowns, 2 of 2, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - A Thousand Clowns T-shirt, 2001 (Box 8)
  - Paper Dolls, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - R. Crumb Comix, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Shimada: Paul Berkowsky, Richard Seider, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Van Johnson: Alan Foshko (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - A Week in the Woods, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - You Touched Me: Tennessee Williams, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Misc (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Misc Clippings (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Playbills (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Laughter on 23rd Floor, betacam-sp (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-Bcam-0052)
    Discussion@Cafe
  - Columbus 1492 (Box 6, Audio-cassette UA254002-CS-0001)
    Duke Univesity MCU
  - Tom Selleck: Regis, VHS (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-VHS-0003)
    Discovering America, Christopher Bishop
  - News Segments on A Thousand Clowns, VHS (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-VHS-0004)
  - News Segments on A Thousand Clowns (Copy 2), VHS (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-VHS-0004)
    WNCN-NBC17 (2 segments); WRAL-TV5; WRAZ-Fox 50; WTVD-ABC 11
  - Kudzu Musical, 2/17/1998; VHS (Box 6, Video-cassette UA254002-VHS-0005)
    WNCN-NBC17 (2 segments), WRAL-TV5, WRAZ-Fox 50, WTVD-ABC 11
  - Kudzu T-shirt, 1998 (Box 8)
  - A Thousand Clowns
  - A Thousand Clowns: Playbill